Finding Aid for Munger Family papers, 1793-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Munger Family papers 1793-1945
Munger Family
1 linear foot
00108 Aa 2
Family of Baptist ministers from New York state and southwestern Michigan; papers of Harvey Munger, his son William L. Munger, William's wife Octavia and other members of the Munger, Griffin, and Brown family.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was contributed to the library by John and Ruth Munger (donor no. 8940 ) in 2000, and by William Boothby (donor no. 9940 ), in September 2007.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Harvey Munger (1812-1862) was a Baptist minister active in southwestern Michigan; his son William Munger (1845-1908), also a Baptist minister, graduated from Kalamazoo College in 1871 and, after attending the Rochester Theological Seminary, married Octavia Griffin Munger, in 1877. While attending the seminary in Rochester, Munger befriended Walter Rauschenbusch, a prominent Baptist minister and the founder of the Social Gospel Movement. The two remained very close throughout their lives and greatly influenced each other's theological beliefs. William Munger was also active as the field secretary of the Michigan Anti-Saloon League. He was also on the board of Kalamazoo College for nearly forty years.
Octavia Griffin Munger, too, came from a line of Baptist ministers including her father, Harold Griffin, and her grandfather, Solomon Brown--a veteran of the American Revolution who then settled in New York State. Octavia was born in southwest Michigan and attended Kalamazoo College where she met Harvey Munger. She was active in the Michigan Woman's Baptist Missionary Society. William and Octavia had four children, Griffin, Lura, Nelson, and Florence.
The collection is organized by family member. The papers of Harvey Munger include correspondence and a journal/account book (1835-1847). The papers of William L. Munger include letters received from Walter Rauschenbusch (1886-1918), sermons, writings and articles, and other papers relating to his activities with the Michigan Anti- Saloon League. The Octavia Griffin Munger papers include correspondence with family members and friends, writings, and papers relating to her work with the Woman's Baptist Home and Missionary Society of Michigan. There are also small files of materials from other members of the Munger family that primarily contain correspondence. Of note are papers of Solomon Brown dating back to the eighteenth century and a letter received by Nancy Brown in 1841 from Sault Ste. Marie missionary, Abel Bingham, 1841. The collection also includes a copy of a letter written by Angie Bingham Gilbert describing events surrounding the murder of James Schoolcraft by John Tanner. Tanner had formerly been a captive of the Indians in the 1840s in the Sault Ste. Marie area of Michigan.
Subjects:
Munger family.; Clergy--Michigan.; Anti-Saloon League of Michigan.; Brown, Solomon, 1757-1815.; Missionaries--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Munger, Harvey, 1812-1862.; Munger, William L., 1845-1908.; Munger, Octavia.; Murder--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Rauschenbusch, Walter 1861-1918.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.)--History.; Schoolcraft, James L.; Tanner, John 1780?-1847.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Woman's Baptist Home and Foreign Missionary Societies of Michigan.; Temperance--Michigan.
Contributors:
Bingham, Abel 1786-1865.; Brown, Solomon, 1757-1815.; Gilbert, Angelina Bingham.; Munger, Harvey, 1812-1862.; Munger, William L., 1845-1908.; Munger, Octavia.; Rauschenbusch, Walter 1861-1918.
Genre Terms:
Sermons
- Harvey Munger
  - Correspondence, 1830-1859 and undated (Box 1)
  - Journal/Account Book, 1835-1847 (Box 1)
- William L. Munger
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Letters received, 1883-1908 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Walter Rauschenbusch, 1886-1918 and undated, 7 folders (Box 1)
    (some of the letters addressed to Mrs. Munger)
  - Michigan Anti-Saloon League (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
    (include photographic portrait of, and other material about, Walter Rauschenbusch)
  - Sermons (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of Newspaper and Journal Articles (Box 1)
  - Support for position of chaplain at Jackson Prison (Box 1)
- Octavia Griffin Munger
  - Correspondence, 1861-1936 and undated, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Woman's Baptist Home and Missionary Society of Michigan, 1870 and undated (Box 1)
  - Writings (Box 1)
- Other Munger family members
  - Rhoda Munger
    - Album of sentiments, 1846 (Box 1)
  - Florence Boothby (née Munger)
    - Correspondence, 1908-1931 and undated (Box 1)
  - Lura Munger
    - Correspondence and Graduation Speech, 1908-1938 and undated (Box 1)
  - Nelson Munger
    - Correspondence, 1908-1914 and undated (Box 1)
  - John Munger
    - Letter from Iran, 1945 (Box 1)
- Griffin and Brown family papers
  - Correspondence between Solomon Brown and Parker Reynolds, 1793-1794 (Box 1)
  - Solomon Brown's Writing, 1780s-1790s (Box 1)
  - H.M. Griffin Correspondence, 1864-1870 (Box 1)
  - Griffin-Brown genealogical and biographical material (Box 1)
  - Nancy Brown. Letter from Abel Bingham, 1841 (Box 1)
    (original and typescript)
  - Lucy Ann Griffin. Letter to her mother, 1846 (Box 1)
  - Angie Bingham Gilbert. Letter (typescript), November 14, 1899 to Peter White describing events surrounding the murder of James Schoolcraft by John Tanner (Box 1)
    (Tanner had formerly been a captive of the Indians)
- Other families and miscellaneous
  - Zenos and Henry Case Family materials, 1846-1854 and undated (Box 1)
  - Church covenants, 1857 and undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogical and biographical information; also photocopies of family photographs (Box 1)
  - Family related newspaper clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and various correspondence, 1840-1936 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and publications (Box 1)